<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" revision="$Id: ConnectingDevice.xml 752 2015-03-02 06:09:11Z ljp $" xml:id="section.connecting-device">
    <title>Connecting the device </title>
    <para>The tracker is connected to the server in one of three ways each with there own advantages
        and disadvantages.</para>
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Direct with a <acronym>USB</acronym> cable</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Pros:</emphasis></emphasis>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Does not incur any cost.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Does not require special setup</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Cons:</emphasis></emphasis>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The tracker must be physically close to the server</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>This can be done even without the daemon but will require the user to
                            set up a serial connection to the device and use software to communicate
                            with the device.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Over <acronym>GPRS</acronym></para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Pros:</emphasis></emphasis>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Allows server to control the device over a distance which makes it
                            easy for the end user</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Cons:</emphasis></emphasis>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Consumes bandwidth and incur costs</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Requires a server software to talk to the device</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Requires the setup of device GPRS connection which will drain the
                            battery. Due to the way a connection is established a constant
                            connection must be established by regularly sending data even when the
                            end user has made no such requests. The daemon will automatically send
                            data as necessary to keep the connection alive.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Using <acronym>GSM</acronym> text messages (a.k.a <acronym>SMS</acronym>,
                    <emphasis role="italic">Short Message Service</emphasis>)</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Pros:</emphasis></emphasis>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Can control the device over distance</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Does not require any extra software or server</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Cons:</emphasis></emphasis>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Incur cost for each message (both in sending phone and in device since
                            a reply is normally sent)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Tedious and error prone to enter long commands as texts</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Requires the user to learn the detailed device protocol</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
        </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <section>
        <title>Connecting over USB</title>
        <para>This only requires a mini USB cable between the device and your computer. When a new
            device have been connected the daemon will automatically detect this and when the device
            is ready it will read back the device ID. The connected <acronym>USB</acronym> devices
            can be listed with the "<command>.usb</command>" command. The active USB port (the one
            receiving the given commands) is indicated with a '*'. Withe the same command it is
            possible to select which of the connected devices should receive the commands (See <xref
                xlink:href="#cmd.srv-usb"/>). Please allow for 20s after the device have been
            attached to the computer for the connection to be fully established and it will start to
            accept commands.</para>
        <para>If no device is connected an error message will be shown if you try to give commands
            to the device (unless you are using a debug version of the daemon configured with the
                <literal>--enable-simulate</literal> option, see <xref
                xlink:href="#section.build-environment"/>). An easy way to verify that the device is
            recognized is to query the device, for example by asking for the version of the firmware
            via the "<literal>get ver</literal>" command.</para>
        <para>
            <important>
                <para>On Linux the user running the daemon must have read/write access to the
                        <acronym>USB</acronym> device (usually <literal>ttyACM0</literal> or
                    similar). On most system this requires the user to be a member of the
                        "<literal>dialout</literal>" group. </para>
            </important>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Configuring USB connection</title>
        <para>On Linux the <acronym>USB</acronym> connections shows up as a
                <literal>ttyACM</literal><emphasis role="italic">n</emphasis> but on
                <productname>OSX</productname> it shows up as
                <literal>cu.usbmodem</literal><emphasis role="italic">nnnn</emphasis>. To help the
            daemon identify the device it is necessary to specify the correct number in the config
            file. On Linux based system it usually doesn't matter what <acronym>USB</acronym> port
            you connect on, it will still give the device to the same <literal>ttyACM</literal>
            device. The ports are numbered from 0 unless you have a number of other peripheral
            permanently connected. In that case you most likely need to set a higher start number
            then "0" i the configuration file so that the daemon does not try to connect to the
            other peripheral.</para>
        <para>However, for <acronym>OSX</acronym> this number will differ depending on which
                <acronym>USB</acronym> port you connect the device on. Therefore you should check
            which device it shows up as by listing the devices under the "<filename>/dev</filename>"
            directory. On <productname>OSX</productname> this will be a 4 digit number (e.g. 1411)
            but on Linux it will be a single digit number. The config file setting for this is the
                <literal>stty_device</literal> variable at the top of the config file. For
                <productname>OSX</productname> a list of possible <acronym>USB</acronym> ports to
            watch can be given since they are not numbered sequentially as they are on Linux.</para>
        <para>
            <note>
                <para>The connection over <acronym>USB</acronym> on <productname>OSX</productname>
                    should be considered an experimental feature. The connection can sometimes have
                    a temperament and <productname>OSX</productname> might refuse to recognize a
                    connected device. In case of problem try reconnect the device after it been to
                    sleep and woken up. The cause for the (sometimes) instability on
                        <productname>OSX</productname> is so far unknown. </para>
                <para>The <acronym>USB</acronym> connection on Linux is however extremly stable and
                    hence should be the preferred platform when working with devices over
                        <acronym>USB</acronym>.</para>
            </note>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Connecting over GPRS</title>
        <para>It is possible to send command to the device remotely over <acronym>GPRS</acronym>. In
            order for this to work it is first necessary to enable <acronym>GPRS</acronym> as a
            communication channel. This is done using the "<command>comm</command>" command (<xref
                xlink:href="#cmd.comm"/>). Once this is setup the device will constantly be in touch
            with the base over GPRS. Please note that this will drain the battery fairly soon so it
            should only be used on devices with external power supply or for a short period of time. </para>
        <para>Since it is possible for the daemon to have multiple trackers connected either on
                <acronym>USB</acronym> or over <acronym>GPRS</acronym> the daemon must be told which
            tracker to send commands to. This is done with either the "<command>.usb</command>"
            command (<xref xlink:href="#cmd.srv-usb"/>) which specifies the <acronym>USB</acronym>
            target for the following commands or by the <command>.target</command> (<xref
                linkend="cmd.srv-target"/>) command hich specifies
            the <acronym>GPRS</acronym> target for the following commands. A target can be specified
            with either its nick-name or its client number as listed by the "<command>.ld</command>"
            command.</para>
        <para>
            <tip>
                <para>To make it easier configure the preset "<command>gprs_on</command>" to enable
                        <acronym>GPRS</acronym> communication. Please note however that the exact
                    setting the preset template must be customized with the details of the operator
                    providing the <acronym>SIM</acronym> used in the device.</para>
            </tip>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Connecting with text messages</title>
        <para>Please see the supplied manual for the tracker. This requires no special setup on the
            behalf of the daemon.</para>
    </section>
</section>

