<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"   xml:id="section.controlling-device">
    <title>Controlling the device using commands</title>
    <para>A tracking device such as the <productname>GM7</productname> must be setup to operate in a
        specific mode to be useful. The tracker can be setup so that it only sends an update when it
        detects a movement or for example when the speed exceeds a certain limit. There are three
        major way in which the device can be configured as discussed in <xref
            linkend="section.connecting-device"/>. </para>
    <para>The daemon supports both communication over <acronym>USB</acronym> which is the preferred
        way to do the initial setup </para>
    <para>Please keep in mind though that when you are giving commands you are talking to the daemon
        which then sends commands to the device. The normal way to interact with the daemon is
        through the command shell , "<literal>g7sh</literal>", see  <xref
            linkend="section.command-shell"/>.</para>
    <section>
        <title>Controlling the device using server commands</title>
        <para>The device has its own set of "raw" commands that can be used to communicate with the
            device. These commands are described in the protocol description fro the
                <productname>GM7 Tracker</productname>. These are for example the commands you would
            use when sending text messages to the device. The problem with this is that the syntax
            is a bit tedious and it requires the user to look up or remember the exact meaning of a
            number of arguments given to each command.</para>
        <para>
            <note>
                <para>Using the commands below assumes that a device is connected via the
                        <acronym>USB</acronym> port. If this is not so the daemon will give a
                    information message that device commands are not available at this time.</para>
            </note>
        </para>
        <para>To alleviate this burden a bit the daemon has its own command set that is easier for
            an end user to remember and use. As an example consider the following "raw"
            command</para>
        <para>
            <screen>$WP+ROAM=0000,1</screen>
        </para>
        <para>which is used to enable <acronym>GSM</acronym>/<acronym>GPRS</acronym> roaming (i.e.
            the device can send text and data when the <acronym>SIM</acronym> card is in roaming
            mode). </para>
        <para>The same command using the simplified daemon command set would be</para>
        <para>
            <screen>> set roam on</screen>
        </para>
        <para>Perhaps not a gigantic difference but definitely easier to remember especially since
            the command structure is the same for a large number of commands. The greatest
            difference is however in using commands with many parameters. For example to setup the
            device to use <acronym>GPRS</acronym> communication for a Telenor <acronym>SIM</acronym>
            card assuming the daemon is running on a server with <acronym>IP</acronym> address
                <literal>158.94.13.298</literal> on port <literal>3100</literal> with 45s in between
            the so called <literal>KEEP_ALIVE </literal>packets the raw command to send the device
            would be</para>
        <para>
            <screen>$WP+COMMTYPE=0000,4,,,services.telenor.se,,,158.94.13.298,3100,45,</screen>
        </para>
        <para>The chances of getting this command right every time from memory is very small indeed.
            Using the daemons command version instead the following conversation between the user
            and the daemon would take place:</para>
        <para>
            <screen>> set comm
CommSelect - Select primary type of communication
  0 - Use USB
  1 - Use SMS over GSM
  2 - CSD &lt;reserved>
  3 - UDP over GPRS
  4 - TCP/IP over GPRS
Select (0/1/2/3/4)?
>> </screen>
        </para>
        <para>At this point user enters his selection after the "<literal>>></literal>" mark and
            hits enter. The next question will be</para>
        <para>
            <screen>SMS Base Phone - SMS base number to call
>></screen>
        </para>
        <para>and the user can enter the corresponding phone number. This will be followed by the a
            clear question for each of the following command arguments. After the user have answered
            all the questions and the daemon has made some sanity checks of the answers the complete
            command will be sent to the device. </para>
        <para>
            <note>
                <para>When giving arguments for a device command the prompt changes from "> " to ">>
                    "</para>
            </note>
        </para>
        <para>To further simplify device handling it is possible to "record" command and command
            sequences so that instead of having to answer ten questions (as is the case for the
            "comm" command) a single command is given and earlier recorded parameters are used See
                <xref linkend="section.using-presets"/>.</para>
        <para>
            <tip>
                <para>To abort a command in the middle of specifying parameters just enter a
                    punctuation character "<command>.</command>" to abort the current
                    command.</para>
            </tip>
        </para>
        <para>A complete list of server command with all argument s given in <xref
                linkend="appendix.command-reference"/>. Below is a one line summary of all
            available server commands as printed by the daemon "<literal>help</literal>"
            command.</para>
        <para>
            <tip>
                <para>It is also possible to enter commands bypassing the argument questions. For
                    details see <xref linkend="sec.direct-device-commands"/></para>
            </tip>
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Device Command list:
--------------------
address   - Return the current location as the closest street address
batt      - Read the battery voltage from device
clrec     - Erase all stored locations from the device memory
comm      - Set/Read device communication type and its parameters
config    - Set/Read device ID, Password, and PIN Code of the SIM card
dlrec     - Download all stored locations in device memory to DB
gfen      - Enable/Disabling virtual fence
gfevt     - Enable/Disable/Set/Read GEO-Fencing event
imei      - Query the IMEI number of the internal GSM module
led       - Enable/Disable the LED indicator on/off
loc       - Get latest location
locg      - Get latest location as a Google map string
lowbatt   - Set/Read the internal battery low level alert
mswitch   - Set handling of detach event
nrec      - Get number of locations in device memory
phone     - Enable the function "Get the current location by making a phone call"
ps        - Enable/Disable power saving mode
reboot    - Restart-up the device
rec       - Enable/Disable/read logging function to the device
reset     - Reset all parameters to the manufactory default settings
roam      - Enable/Disable GPRS roaming function
sim       - Query the identification of the SIM card
sleep     - Enable/Disable "Sleeping Report"
sms       - Switch the SMS format (Text of PDU mode)
test      - Device diagnostic function
track     - Control if device should be sending back automatic tracking information.
tz        - Set the time zone information for the device
ver       - Get current firmware version
vip       - Preset up to 5 SMS phone numbers for receiving different alerts

Use "help &lt;command>" for detailed help on each command.

Server Command list:
--------------------
help       - Print help for all commands
.lookup    - Toggle geolocation lookup
.cachestat - Print statistics of cache usage
.date      - Print date and time of server
.target    - List or set the GPRS target device to be active
.usb       - List or set USB connected device to be active
.ver       - Give version information of server
.lc        - List active connections
.ld        - List all connected devices (both on USB and GPRS)
.nd        - Delete specified nick
.nick      - Register a nick-name for connected device
.nl        - List all registered nicks
.table     - Toggle pretty printing of tables
.ratereset - Allow calls to the Google location API after usage limit excess

DB Command list:
----------------
db dist            - Calculate the approximate distance from a set of chosen locations
db deletelocations - Clear all stored locations
db export          - Export selected locations in chosen format to file
db head            - Display locations in DB from the top
db lastloc         - Retrieve the last stored location in the DB
db mailpos         - Mail the last stored location in the DB
db mailgpx         - Export the database in GPX format and mail as compressed attachment
db mailcsv         - Export the database in CSV format and mail as compressed attachment
db size            - Report number of location events in DB
db tail            - Display locations in DB from the head

Preset command list:
----------------
preset list            - List all read preset files with short description
preset refresh         - Re-read all preset files from disk
preset use &lt;preset>    - Use (execute) the specified preset ("@&lt;preset>" as shortform)
preset help &lt;preset>   - Give more detailed help on the specified preset</screen>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="sec.direct-device-commands">
            <title>Non-Interactive device commands - the @@CMD(arg1, ...) format</title>
            <para>By default all device commands are interactive in the sense that giving a command
                will interactively ask for all arguments interactively one by one explaining the
                purpose of the command and the choice of input. For example for the <command>set
                    comm</command> command the interaction would be somewhat along the lines of (all
                text <emphasis role="bold">in bold</emphasis> are user input):</para>
            <para>
                <screen>> <emphasis role="bold">set comm</emphasis>
CommSelect - Select primary type of communication
  0 - Use USB
  1 - Use SMS over GSM
  2 - CSD &lt;reserved>
  3 - UDP over GPRS
  4 - TCP/IP over GPRS
Select (0/1/2/3/4)?
>> <emphasis role="bold">4</emphasis>
SMS Base Phone - SMS base number to call?
>> <emphasis role="bold">[RETURN]</emphasis>
CSD Base Phone - CSD base number &lt;reserved and not used>?
>> <emphasis role="bold">[RETURN]</emphasis>
GPRS APN - The operators APN?
>> <emphasis role="bold">internet.telenor.se</emphasis>
GPRS User - User name if required?
>> <emphasis role="bold">[RETURN]</emphasis>
GPRS Passwd - Password if required?
>> <emphasis role="bold">[RETURN]</emphasis>
GPRS Server - Server IP address where the device reports back to?
>> <emphasis role="bold">mytracker.mydomain.com</emphasis>
GPRS Server Port - TCP/IP Port to use on server?
>> <emphasis role="bold">3400</emphasis>
GPRS Keep Alive - Interval (in sec) between Keep Alive Packets?
>> <emphasis role="bold">120</emphasis>
GPRS DNS - Optional DNS server for device to use.?
>> <emphasis role="bold">208.67.222.222</emphasis>
[GM7] 4,,,internet.telenor.se,,,mytracker.mydomain.com,3400,120,208.67.222.222
      CommSelect: TCP/IP over GPRS
  SMS Base Phone: 
  CSD Base Phone: 
        GPRS APN: internet.telenor.se
       GPRS User: 
     GPRS Passwd: 
     GPRS Server: aditus.asuscomm.com
GPRS Server Port: 3400
 GPRS Keep Alive: 120
        GPRS DNS: 208.67.222.222

% 
</screen>
            </para>
            <para>Entering an empty line leaves the original value intact. To clear an old value (to
                leave it empty) enter an empty string (<emphasis role="bold">""</emphasis>).</para>
            <para>The above sequence makes sense for most users since it can not be expected to
                memorize the arguments for the many possible commands. However , for experienced
                users (or to use the command shell non-interactively) it is also possible to enter
                the commands non-interactively and not have the question for each argument posed.
                The format for this is</para>
            <para>
                <screen>@@COMMAND(arg1,arg2,...)</screen>
            </para>
            <para>So to enter the above command as a non-interactive command a user would
                enter</para>
            <para>
                <screen>% @@COMM(4,,,internet.telenor.se,,,mytracker.mydomain.com,3400,120,208.67.222.222)
OK.
% </screen>
            </para>
            <para>As explained above it is necessary to use the empty string ("") to clear a value
                instead of just leaving it empty which will keep the old value.</para>
            <para>
                <screen>% @@COMM(4,"","",internet.telenor.se,"","",mytracker.mydomain.com,3400,120,208.67.222.222)
OK.
% </screen>
            </para>
            <para>
                <note>
                    <para>Please note that (by design) spaces are now allowed in the function
                        call.</para>
                </note>
            </para>
            <para>The main purpose of this possibility is to be able to script command sequences
                using the command shell ( g <command>g7sh</command>) with the "<emphasis
                    role="italic">-e</emphasis>" option that can send commands to the daemon
                non-interactively. Of course, experienced user might find this faster than to have
                to answer a sequence of questions once the arguments have been understood and
                memorized.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Controlling the device using "raw" device commands</title>
        <para>In order to accommodate expert users that really wants to use the raw commands
            directly the server also makes this possible. Raw device commands can be seen as an even
            more complex alternative to the  "<literal>@@</literal>" non-interactive functions. This
            makes it possible to interact with the device on the lowest level by giving commands
            directly according to their exact syntax as described in the <emphasis role="italic">GM7
                Protocol description</emphasis>.</para>
        <para>For example. to find the <acronym>IMEI</acronym> number of the device give the
            command</para>
        <para>
            <screen>$WP+IMEI=0000,?</screen>
        </para>
        <para>To enable this the config file setting "<literal>enable_raw_commands</literal>" must
            be set to true. <emphasis role="bold">Please note that by default this option is
                disabled</emphasis>. This should be considered an expert options and we refer to the
                <emphasis role="italic">GM7 Protocol description</emphasis> for details on the exact
            format for the command string and we will not discuss this further here.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section.using-presets">
        <title>Using presets</title>
        <para>Presets is way to record often used commands or command sequences. Technically this is
            a file of one or more commands that can be replayed. Any number of commands can be
            given.</para>
        <para>By default the device comes with a few defined presets that will handle common tasks
            such as setting up <acronym>GPRS</acronym> communication and enable tracking.</para>
        <para>All preset files are stored in "<filename>/usr/share/g7ctrl/presets/</filename>" and
            have file suffix "<literal>.preset</literal>". The following commands are available to
            manage presets.</para>
        <para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">preset list</emphasis></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>List all currently defined presets</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">preset refresh</emphasis></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Refresh all presets from the disk. This command makes it possible to
                            add or remove presets without having to restart the daemon.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">preset use
                            </emphasis><parameter>&lt;preset-name></parameter></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Run the commands in the specified preset file</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">preset help</emphasis>
                        <parameter>&lt;preset-name></parameter></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Each preset file has its own built-in help to remember the user of
                            what exactly each preset file is doing. This command will give the
                            detailed help for the specified preset command.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </para>
        <para>To further simplify running command presets a short form of "<literal>preset use
                &lt;command-name></literal>" exists. </para>
        <para>
            <screen>@&lt;preset-name></screen>
        </para>
        <para>As of version 2.1.3 the following predefined preset template are shipped</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>gprs_on</literal> - This will enable GPRS as the main
                        communication method for the device to report back. It will assume a Telenor
                            <acronym>SIM</acronym> card to set up the APN.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>gprs_off</literal> - Turn the GPRS off. This is opertor
                        independent.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>gtrack_on</literal> - Enable GPRS and tracking. The device will
                        report back its position every 2min</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>gtrack_off</literal> - Disable tracking and GPRS
                        communication</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>alarm_on</literal> - Enable communication over GPRS, Use power
                        save mode 3, Enable GFEN alarm with 100m radius</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>alarm_off </literal>- Disable GFEN alarm</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>rec_on</literal> - Record positions to device memory</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>rec_off</literal> - Stop recording positions to device
                        memory</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>sleep_wm</literal> - Put device in sleep mode 3, wake up on
                        movements and all radios off</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
            <note>
                <para>The shipped files are only templates and must be completed and renamed before
                    they can be run. See <xref linkend="section.preset-templates"/> for
                    details.</para>
            </note>
        </para>
        <para>So if you have a Telenor <acronym>SIM</acronym> card all you have to do to enable the
            device to start sending back location updates every 2min is to connect the device to
            your computer running the daemon using a <acronym>USB</acronym> cable, wait for the
            device to setup communication, start the command shell and give the command</para>
        <para>
            <screen>@gtrack_on</screen>
        </para>
        <para>Assuming you have a Telenor <acronym>SIM</acronym> card the device should now start
            sending back location updates to your server (assuming it is accessible from the
            internet as described in <xref linkend="section.receiving-data"/>). You can verify
            this by requesting the last received location update stored in the database with the
            command</para>
        <para>
            <screen>db lastloc</screen>
        </para>
        <para>which would return something like</para>
        <para>
            <screen>20131010 22:31:19, devid=3000000001, lat=59.4512 lon=17.1853, \
http://maps.google.com/maps?q=59.4512,17.1853</screen>
        </para>
        <para>Verify that the device id and time is what you expect. You should also wait another
            2min and do the same request again to see that a new location has been received. Another
            way would be to review the logfile of the daemon since each connection and location
            update is logged.</para>
        <para> </para>
        <para>
            <note>
                <para>Remember that if the device is not connected to the computer over r
                        <acronym>USB</acronym> it will by default go into sleep mode if no movement
                    is detected within 3min and it will stop sending location updates.</para>
            </note>
        </para>
        <section>
            <title>Adding new presets</title>
            <para>Presets are created by adding a new file (with the file suffix
                    "<literal>.preset</literal>" in the preset directory. Each preset file has a
                comment section at top which is shown when the preset help &lt;preset> is given and
                then one or more commands. A comment line is started with a "<literal>#</literal>"
                character. </para>
            <para>The commands are the same as the daemon commands but written as function calls
                with parenthesis. As an example the following preset file sets up
                    <acronym>GPRS</acronym> communication and starts a device tracking (i.e. the
                device sends back location data at regular interval) and sending it back to the
                server at <acronym>IP</acronym> address <literal>85.226.91.109</literal></para>
            <para>
                <programlisting>#Enable GPRS tracking
#This enable GPRS tracking back to a sever
# Using Telenor APN (internet.telenor.se)
# Server is 85.226.91.109, and port=3400
# Keep alive packet are sent every 45s
# Tracking every 2min regardless GPS fix
comm(4,"","",internet.telenor.se,"","",85.226.91.109,3400,45,"")
track(1,120,0,35,1,4,15)</programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>As can be seen the commands have to include all arguments even if they are empty.
                The command reference (see <xref linkend="appendix.command-reference"/>) lists
                all commands and there arguments.</para>
            <para>To refresh the preset files remember to either restart the daemon or run
                    "<command>preset refresh</command>" after a new preset file has been
                added.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="section.preset-templates">
            <title>Preset templates</title>
            <para>To make it easy the daemon includes a number of predefined preset template (for
                example "<filename>gtrack.preset.template</filename>". This preset will both enable
                the <acronym>GPRS</acronym> communication and also turn on tracking so that the
                device will start sending updates at specified time interval.)</para>
            <para>The template preset must be edited according to your preferences and operator details.
                It should be clear in the template where to edit from the placeholder. </para>
            <para>For example to adapt the <literal>gtrack</literal> template do the following</para>
            <para>Start by copying the template to a file without the <literal>.template</literal>
                suffix.</para>
            <para>
                <screen>cp gtrack.preset.template gtrack.preset</screen>
            </para>
            <para>Then change the IP-address of your server, the time interval and the
                    <literal>KEEP_ALIVE</literal> time. The template is shown in the listing below
                with the placeholder you should change marked in bold</para>
            <para>
                <programlisting>#Enable GPRS tracking
#This enable GPRS tracking back to a sever on port 3400
#Using Telenor APN (internet.telenor.se)
comm(4,"","",internet.telenor.se,"","",<emphasis role="bold">[SERVER_IP]</emphasis>,3400,<emphasis role="bold">[KEEPALIVE_TIME]</emphasis>,"")
track(1,<emphasis role="bold">[TRACKTIME_SEC]</emphasis>,0,0,1,4,15)</programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><literal>SERVER_IP</literal></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>IP Address of server</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><literal>KEEPALIVE_TIME</literal></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Keep alive time in seconds (usually in the range 30-180)</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><literal>TRACKTIME_SEC</literal></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Tracking interval in seconds for the device to send back position
                                update to server</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </para>
            <para>The above preset assumes that you have a Telenor <acronym>SIM</acronym> so it uses
                the Telenor <acronym>APN</acronym> (<literal>internet.telenor.se</literal>) and that
                you are using the default tracker port (<literal>3400</literal>). For a detailed
                explanation of the meaning of all other parameters please see the command reference
                    <xref linkend="appendix.command-reference"/>.</para>
        </section>
        
    </section>
</section>
