<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0"  xml:id="section.installing">
    <title>Installing</title>
    <tip>
        <para>There are pre-built binary packages for <productname>OpenSuSE</productname> 12.1 -
            13.1 (both in <acronym>RPM</acronym> and <emphasis role="italic"
                >One-Click-Install</emphasis>) available from <link
                xlink:href="http://software.opensuse.org/download.html?project=home%3Ajohanp_aditus&amp;package=g7ctrl"
            /></para>
    </tip>
    <section>
        <title>System requirements</title>
        <para>The software is designed to work on a <acronym>GNU</acronym> Linux derived system. It has been built and
            verified on the following systems and versions:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><productname>OpenSuSE</productname> 12.3, 13.1</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><productname>Linux Mint</productname> r15, r16, r17</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">OS X Maverick 10.9</emphasis> (Experimental support
                    only - <command>g7sh</command> has limitations and requires
                        <acronym>GNU</acronym> readline for full functionality, see <xref
                        xlink:href="#section.known-defects"/>)</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>The daemon will specifically <emphasis role="bold">not</emphasis> run on any variant
            of MS Windows nor will it ever be ported by the author to any variants thereof.</para>
        <para>Even though the daemon is only tested on these versions it will most likely build fine
            on most recent <acronym>GNU</acronym> Linux distributions. It does not make use of any
            special code, tricks or requires special libraries. In order to compile the software a
            supported C compiler must be used. As of version 2.0 the following compilers are
            officially supported:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><command>gcc</command>,v4.6.x,  v4.7.x &amp; v4.8.x</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><command>clang</command>, v3.2</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>In addition the daemon need three utility libraries to build. The build configuration
            will check for those libraries and if they are not found an error message is shown on
            exactly what library is missing. For current version of the daemon the following
            external libraries are needed for a successful compilation.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>libpcre3</literal></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>libsqlite3</literal></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>libxml2</literal></para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>In addition, if your system has <literal>libiniparser</literal> library the build will
            also use it and if it is not available a built-in version will be used. In order to
            compile with the needed libraries the development version of each library (usually named
            with a "<literal>-devel</literal>" or "<literal>-dev</literal>" suffix) must be
            installed.</para>
        <para>
            <warning>
                <para>Please make sure that the Tracker firmware is <emphasis role="bold">M7 2.007
                        GP rev00c</emphasis> or later. With the daemon installed and the device
                    connected you can easily verify this using the command <command>get
                        ver</command></para>
            </warning>
        </para>
    </section>    
   <section>
       <title>Building and installing</title>
       <para>Even though the process of installing the daemon ideally is as simple as typing three
            commands it is inevitable that different systems and variants behave differently and it
            is impossible to test the software build on all possible configurations "in the wild".
            While the software is configured to handle most system differences automatically there
            will always be corner cases that will require some minor adjustments to get the software
            working on that particular system. Unfortunately that requires a bit of
            experience.</para>
    <para>It will be helpful if you previously experience running <command>configure</command> and
                <command>make</command>. The commands</para>
    <para>
        <screen>> ./configure &amp;&amp; make
sudo make install</screen>
    </para>
    <para>is a standard way of compiling and installing Unix/<acronym>GNU</acronym> Linux software
            based on the <acronym>GNU</acronym>
            <emphasis role="italic">Automake</emphasis> tool chain (which is a fantastic piece of
            canned black magic and years of experience). With default configuration the daemon will
            be installed in <filename>/usr/bin</filename> and the configuration directory will be
            set to <filename>/etc/g7ctrl</filename>. If you would like to install the daemon in
            other places, for example under <filename>/usr/local/bin</filename>, then configure the
            daemon using the <literal>--prefix</literal> argument as</para>
    <para>
        <screen>> ./configure --prefix=/usr/local &amp;&amp; make
sudo make install</screen>
    </para>
    <para>If you are not comfortable with this process or have never done this before it is
            recommended for you to use a pre-compiled package for your particular system. </para>
    <para> 
        <tip>
            <para>If a package does not yet exist for your system please consider requesting a
                package to be provided from the people responsible for your distribution.</para>
        </tip>
    </para></section>

    <section>
        <title>Installing the daemon as a systemd service</title>
        <para>For technical reason having to do with the way the autotools work the  installation
            does not enable the daemon as a service.  If you want to have the daemon run as a
                <literal>systemd</literal> service execute the following line after you have done
            the standard <literal>make install</literal> (still as root)</para>
        <para>
            <screen>> systemctl enable g7ctrl.service</screen>
        </para>
        <para>This will enable the <command>g7ctrl</command> service with <literal>systemd</literal>
            in multi-user mode. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Rebuilding the documentation</title>
        <para>The distribution comes with pre-rendered versions of all documentation in both plain
            text, <acronym>HTML</acronym> and <acronym>PDF</acronym> format. </para>
        <para>The documentation is written using the <emphasis role="italic">Docbook 5
                XML</emphasis> schema which is a very good way to build multi-mode documentation.
            However, rebuilding the documentation (perhaps you want to add some section or have
            found one or more spelling mistakes that irritates you) requires a fully working Docbook
            5 environment. </para>
        <para>While this is certainly possible <emphasis role="italic">Docbook5</emphasis> and
                <acronym>XML</acronym> transformations might not be everyone’s coup of tea. if you
            are not used to the <acronym>XML</acronym> transformation process it can be a certain
            learning step. The configuration process will investigate your system if it has the
            capability to render all or some of the output formats and state that information at the
            end after running the "<filename>./configure</filename>" script.</para>
        <para>
            <tip>
                <para>An easy way to get a fully working <emphasis role="italic">Docbook5</emphasis>
                    setup is to check out the source directly from the repository and run the
                        <filename>bootstrap.sh</filename> script. This will re-create a full build
                    environment for the daemon. See <xref xlink:href="#section.build-environment"
                    /></para>
            </tip>
        </para>
        <para> </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Configuring and compiling the source using the distributed tarball</title>
        <para>Using the tar-ball installation is the recommended way for most end users (compared to
            getting the source directly from the repository) since the tar ball has pre-built
            configuration environment and pre-rendered documentation. After downloading the tarball
            (please use the latest version available at the time of download) it needs to be
            extracted to a temporary directory where it can be compiled. </para>
        <para>Assuming you have downloaded version 3.0.0 the commands to extract the source is
            first</para>
        <para>
            <screen>> tar xzf g7ctrl-3.0.0.tar.gz</screen>
        </para>
        <para>or if you downloaded the "<literal>.xz</literal>" version (which is in general smaller
            but requires the <command>xz</command>-compression program, which makes use of the more
            efficient <acronym>LMZ2</acronym>)</para>
        <para>
            <screen>> tar xJf g7ctrl.3.0.0.tar.xz</screen>
        </para>
        <para>In order to then configure and compile the sources (using default settings) do the
            following:</para>
        <para>
            <screen>> cd g7ctrl-3.0.0
./configure &amp;&amp; make -j8</screen>
        </para>
        <para>(the <literal>-j8</literal> is strictly speaking not necessary but will speed up the
            compilation a bit through parallelization) If some of the necessary prerequisites are
            missing (like one of the required libraries) an error message will be given. Install the
            required library and run the commands again. Once the compilation process is done the
            daemon needs to be installed. This requires <literal>root</literal> privileges. To
            install the daemon do the following</para>
        <para>
            <screen>> sudo make install</screen>
        </para>
        <para>By default the installation process will install the binary in
                <filename>/usr/bin</filename>, the configuration file in
                <filename>/etc/g7ctrl</filename> and the database in
                <filename>/var/lib/g7ctrl</filename>. The exact location can easily be changed by
            using the "<literal>--prefix</literal>" argument to "<literal>configure</literal>". For
            a complete list of options at configuration time please run </para>
        <para>
            <screen>> ./configure --help</screen>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section.build-environment">
        <titleabbrev>Creating a build environment</titleabbrev>
        <title>Setting up your own build environment - for developers</title>
        <para>If your are planning to do some development of your own or just want to follow the
            development of the daemon more closely than waiting for official releases you can set up
            your own local copy of the repository. However, this is only recommended for developers
            with previous experience with medium complex software. Specifically you need experience
            with the <emphasis>subversion</emphasis>
            <acronym>SCS</acronym> since that is what the repository uses.</para>
        <para>To help setup a full build environment including the
                <productname>Docbook5</productname> environment with this there are two utility
            script in the <filename>bldscripts</filename> directory which when run will
            automatically set up a complete build environment including a working
                <productname>Docbook5</productname> environment. The two included bootstrap scripts
            are</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><filename>bootstrap.sh</filename></para>
                <para>Used for RPM based system like OpenSuSE</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><filename>bootstrap-deb.sh</filename></para>
                <para>Used for PKG based system such as Debian, Ubuntu or Linux Mint</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>The bootstrap script are <emphasis role="bold">only</emphasis> meant to be <emphasis
                role="bold">run once</emphasis> after the initial checkout. </para>
        <para>If you are on a <productname>Debian</productname> based system the following two steps
            are all that is needed to both checkout and setup a complete build system</para>
        <para>
            <screen>> svn co http://www.sourceforge.net/p/g7ctrl/trunk g7ctrl
> cd g7ctrl
> ./bldscripts/bootstrap<emphasis role="bold">-deb</emphasis>.sh</screen>
        </para>
        <para>and if you are on a <productname>OpenSuSE</productname> (<acronym>RPM</acronym>) based
            system use the following steps</para>
        <para>
            <screen>> svn co http://www.sourceforge.net/p/g7ctrl/trunk g7ctrl
> cd g7ctrl
> sh ./bldscripts/bootstrap.sh</screen>
        </para>
        <para>The bootstrap script will install all required pre-requisites including
                <acronym>GNU</acronym>
            <command>autoconfig</command> and <command>automake</command> tools. If no errors were
            found you should see the following information on the screen.</para>
        <para>
            <screen>Build environment is ready.

Now run autoreconf
You can now run "./stdbuild.sh" to build the daemon
and then then run "./mkrelease.sh" to create new releases.</screen>
        </para>
        <para>Now run the <filename>autoreconf</filename> script in order to recreate the
                <acronym>GNU</acronym> autotools setup. After that you can proceed as usual to build
            the source.</para>
        <para>
            <note>
                <para>Please note that you will not have the ability check in changes to the code
                    base by default. To get permission you need to show that you have a substantial
                    contribution and demonstrated clear knowledge at the level required to
                    comprehend the code base. If you believe you meet this requirement contact the
                    author via email stating your request. For more technical information on the
                    source tree please see <xref xlink:href="#appendix.technical"/></para>
            </note>
        </para>
        <para>For development there are two additional configuration parameters that can be given to
            the configures process.</para>
        <para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>--enable-simulate</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>This will allow the execution of commands even though a real device is
                            not connected. Note that if this is enabled the daemon will never be
                            able to communicate with a real device!</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>--enable-stacktrace</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>This will instrument the build so that in case of a
                                <literal>SIGSEGV</literal> (or <literal>SIGABRT</literal>,
                                <literal>SIGBUS</literal>) a limited stack trace will be written to
                                "<filename>/tmp</filename>" to facility debugging. It is also
                            recommended that the system is setup to allow for full core-dump in
                            order to help with the post-mortem debugging. The stack trace is however
                            useful to help analyze a fault at an end user where he/she can mail the
                            stack trace back to the developer for analyze. Ideally a watch daemon
                            should be added to the system that will watch the
                                <filename>/tmp</filename> directory for a stack trace and in that
                            case offer the end user to automatically mail the trace (and mini-dump)
                            back to the developer.</para>
                        <para>
                            <note>
                                <para><literal>--enable-stacktrace</literal> is <emphasis
                                        role="bold">not</emphasis> supported on OSX/Darwin due to
                                    reliance on specific <acronym>GNU</acronym> Linux system
                                    libraries (stack-walking) and will give a configuration error if
                                    enabled on OSX.</para>
                            </note>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Configuring the daemon</title>
        <para>After a successful installation the daemon needs to be configured. This is done by
            adjusting the configuration template file. The first step is to switch to root and then
            use the template provided to create an initial configuration file. Assuming the
            configuration file is installed in the default directory start by doing the
            following:</para>
        <para>
            <screen>> cd /etc/g7ctrl
> sudo cp g7ctrl.conf.template g7ctrl.conf</screen>
        </para>
        <para>The next step is to open the configuration file in your favourite editor and adjust a
            few settings in accordance with your preferences and system. There are very few settings
            that you absolutely have to adjust. Depending on your needs and setup you should as a
            minimum review the following settings:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">SMTP mail server.</emphasis>
                </para>
                <para>If you intend to use the mail functionality of the daemon you need to state
                    the name of the <acronym>SMTP</acronym> server and your credentials (user and
                    password)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Listening ports</emphasis></para>
                <para>Reviewing what ports the daemon is listening on from command and device
                    connections. By default the daemon will listen on port <literal>3100</literal>
                    for commands and on port <literal>3400</literal> for incoming events from the
                    tracking device such as alarms and location updates. The ports can be any number
                    but it is recommended you keep the port range in the range
                        <literal>[1025-9000]</literal> unless you really know what you are
                    doing!</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Connection password</emphasis></para>
                <para>In order to make a command connection to the daemon password must normally be
                    given. By default the build process will create a random 6 letter password in
                    the configuration file. You might want to change this to better suit you
                    environment. If you only intend to have the daemon reachable from your local
                    computer network (and not have the command port open to the entire internet) you
                    might turn off the password to avoid having to type it whenever you want to
                    connect the daemon. </para>
                <para>However, if you have the daemon accessible from the internet <emphasis
                        role="bold">you really, really should have it protected by a password
                    </emphasis>of minimum 8 characters in length. However since the communication is
                    done in plain text it is susceptible for line listening. For a secure
                    communication the command shell should be configured as a login shell so that
                    the communication can easily be done over a encrypted link, more details are
                    available in <xref xlink:href="#section.command-shell"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para> All settings in the configuration file is described in more details in <xref
                xlink:href="#appendix.configuring-the-daemon"/>.</para>
    </section>
</section>
