<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" revision="$Id: Preface.xml 889 2015-03-22 23:40:36Z ljp $">
    <title>Preface</title>
    <para>This is a short guide through a particular software that interacts with a technology that
        almost seamlessly has seeped in to our daily life in a way that very few could have
        predicted even just ten years ago. Satellite position technology is probably one of the most
        sophisticated and advanced technologies in common use today. It builds on a theoretical
        framework so complex that there is no single person that knows all the necessary technology
        in its entirety. The particulars are head spinning even for those of us that claim technical
        expertise in small parts of the system. Yet, this human feat of science and engineering is
        in use by ten-year old´s to find there friends or by their parents making sure the kids is
        safely home after school. A truly remarkable achievement but not without risks as we shall
        see later on.</para>
    <para>As a child I remember seeing a movie where the hero was chasing the bad guys from a
        distance by looking at a blinking dot on green phosphorous screen (although I didn't know it
        was phosphor at the time) and I was entirely convinced that such technologies were in the
        hands of the "spy world". Unfortunately that was not true, it was only film-magic. The
        technology available then did not make such a device practical possible. The only distant
        positioning technology at that time was through radio-triangulation (or radar) like what was
        later used and in fact enforced by commercial shipping, the Decca system, which was
        eventually shut down in the early 2000. </para>
    <para>It is only in the last couple of years that such - once film-only-magic technology - has
        become available as a consumer product by combining different technology strands into one
        unit. In fact a modern GPS tracking device is the successful merge of three major technology
        tracks. The satellite navigational system, the digital radio communication (made financially
        possible by the mobile phone explosion) and the internet and its use of a packet switching
        network based on the TCP/IP protocol stack. The development of these three technology track
        together with its supporting technologies has literally made use of much the science
        progress made in the last three hundred years. Specialist mathematical areas like Galois
        theory and BCH error correcting code made reliable communication possible, the relativity
        theory told us how to compensate when talking to satellites, chemical and physical
        engineering pioneered in the 19:th century made it possible to construct everything from
        batteries to rocket fuel and more. </para>
    <para>Most people do not think about such thing when checking Google Maps for how to find that
        special café in Paris which their favourite magazine recommended (only to discover that they
        were not the only one reading that recommendation). Neither should they, but I cannot
        personally help wonder how it comes that those of us working in research and science have
        done such an utterly poor job of marketing. Asking any person on the main street over the
        age of thirty it is a very high probability that he or she has heard of people like
        Hemingway, Jean-Paul Sartre, Doris Lessing, Lord Byron, Edgar Allan Poe, Yates and other
        humanists and writers even if he or she has never read anything by these authors.</para>
    <para>However, if asking the same question but replacing the names with the likes such as Sophus
        Lie, Niels-Henrik Abel, Emmy Noether, Alexis Hocquenghem, Leonard Euler, Carl F. Gauss or
        Dennis Ritchie very few (if any) have ever heard of them. One of the few exceptions is A.
        Einstein but then mostly as a caricature of a an absent-minded old professor in gray hair. </para>
    <para>I find this asymmetry sad. </para>
    <para>While Hemingway without doubt wrote some great books he has not had the impact on the
        everyday life of people in any way that comes even close to the way the latter names have
        had (without most people knowing it) </para>
    <para>Coming back to GPS technology and its rapid commoditization which actually poses a risk
        that few people are fully aware of. The rapid fall in cost (after the GPS system was
        released to the civil market by the US military - but only after congress threatened to kill
        of the entire program due to cost) has tempted many manufacturer to replace older proven
        technology with cheap mass-market GPS receivers in places not easily guessed. So was the
        fact for example when the British navy commissioned a ship that specifically should be fully
        functional with no GPS. During the tests when the GPS signal was jammed their sonar suddenly
        stopped working. It turned out that the manufacturer of the sonar equipment had made use of
        a GPS receiver inside the sonar (which nobody had thought of) since it was so cheap that
        they practically got it for free. </para> 
    <para>It is therefore worth giving some thoughts about the risk of satellite communication and
        the dependency we as a society in a very short time has built up on this technology. Even
        though getting the wrong position from your stolen car is not helpful it is also hardly a
        life and death situation either. However, a false position for an airplane in mid-air flight
        can cause some fairly interesting situations most people want to avoid. </para>
    <para>What you first realize looking a bit deeper into satellite navigation is that this is a
        scaringly fragile technology. With equipment that can (almost) be purchased at the closest
        Wall-Mart for the cost of a better dinner you can interfere with equipment worth billions of
        dollars. The current GPS system was never truly designed to be a technology able to robustly
        run the world to the extent we have now come to rely on as the following two recent stories
        illustrates.</para>
    <para>In 2011 Newark airport in the USA experienced sporadic problem with their GPS system to
        the extent that it was forced to divert airplanes to other airports or put them in long
        holding positions until the airports GPS system was back online (and double checked). The
        technicians and the manufacture spent months of trying to pinpoint the problem without
        success. The problem was randomly occurring and no pattern could be discovered. As the
        suspicion of sabotage grew the police was contacted and a massive surveillance operation was
        put in place to discover any outside influence of the airport system. The problem continued
        but no unauthorized personal was discovered. As a last resort the team set up cameras on the
        highway outside the airport and started filming all cars driving there. After a couple of
        months with some more disturbances the police started a painfully detailed analysis of the
        films in the hope of detecting some patterns correlating with the disturbances.</para>
    <para>The pattern was found. With the films it was clear that a specific truck had been driving
        close to the airport every time the GPS signal was lost. The police concluded that this was
        deliberate sabotage and set up a massive operation to intercept the presumed terrorist(s).
        After some time the same truck was spotted and the truck was forced to stop and the driver
        immediately detained (with some mild persuasion we can assume).</para>
    <para>So what had happened, was this in fact the work of domestic terrorists? No, not at all 
        that exciting, the truth was much more mundane. 
        The driver was working for a company that had put in GPS
        tracking devices in all its trucks. Furthermore the drivers were told not to drive there
        trucks home and keep to recommended routes and speeds. This particular driver did not like
        that policy and that the owners wold be able to see exactly how and where he had been driving and as a
        result he had purchased a $99.99 GPS jammer so he could drive his truck without the company
        knowing exactly where and when. Without him knowing it the jammer was more powerful than he
        realized so that whenever he was in the vicinity of the airport the jammer also interfered
        with the highly sensitive equipment in the airport. </para>
    <para>In this story the driver obviously had no malicious intent towards the airport and he was
        later released. However that is not always the case.</para>
    <para>The airport in Soul - South Korea - did experience problem with the traffic systems GPS in
        april-may 2012. Investigations (and satellite surveillance) concluded that directed GPS
        antennas had been constructed in North Korea in the Kaesong area (only ~10km from the
        border). The construction had no other discernible purpose than to interfere with the GPS in
        the airport in Soul. This is black mail on large scale and there is absolutely nothing
        (legally) to do about it. </para>
    <para>So even if the GPS tracker makes for a great anti-theft device for the average "joy-rider"
        you should probably not just yet throw away your lock and key. It might also be a good idea
        to teach you existing or future kids how to use a map &amp; compass and not just trust that
        Google maps will always be available (or accurate)!</para>
    <para>  </para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Happy tracking!</emphasis></para>
    <para>Johan Persson</para>
    <para>@ <emphasis role="italic">N 59.655070, E 14.867005</emphasis></para>
    <para>August 2014</para>
    <para><emphasis role="italic">(Third printing may 2015 to match new features in
            v3.2.x)</emphasis></para>
    <para> </para>
    <section>
        <title>Acknowledgement</title>
        <para>I would like to express my gratitude to <emphasis role="bold">GPSER Sweden
                AB</emphasis> (<link xlink:href="http://gpser.se/">http://gpser.se/</link>) who
            provided the details of the GM7 communication protocol without this project would not
            have been possible.</para>
    </section>
</section>

