<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0"  xml:id="section.receiving-data">
    <title>Receiving data</title>
    <para>Once the daemon is running it will listen for incoming events from the tracker. By default
        the daemon is listening on <acronym>TCP/IP</acronym> port 3400 for device connections. As
        explained in <xref linkend="appendix.configuring-the-daemon"/> the port can be changed
        in either the configuration file or via command line arguments when the daemon is
        started.</para>
    <section>
        <title>Setting up device to receive location updates</title>
        <para>To have the device start sending data two things must happen:</para>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The device must be put in <acronym>GPRS</acronym> communication mode. This
                        is done via the "<command>comm</command>" command in the daemon which will
                        configure the communication method of the device. </para>
                    <para>In order to enable <acronym>GPRS</acronym> communication you must first
                        find out some information from the operator you are using. At minimum you
                        need to find your operators <acronym>APN</acronym> name and if you want to
                        use a <acronym>DNS</acronym> name for your server (as opposed to a numeric
                            <acronym>IP</acronym> address).</para>
                    <para>The final bit of information/decision you need to make is decide how often
                        the device will "phone home". Since the operator has to manage a lot of
                        devices (where most of them are mobile phones) and there is a limited number
                        of IP addresses the operator will re-use addresses when it decides it is not
                        longer in use. The operator assumes a device does no longer need its
                        communication path if it has been silent for a certain time. When the device
                        starts talking again a new IP address and communication path will be
                        setup.</para>
                    <para>Therefore to keep the channel open with the same address the device will
                        regularly send a message back to the server to indicate that the device is
                        alive and kicking even if it hasn't sent any other events in a while.</para>
                    <para>When establishing a <acronym>GPRS</acronym> connection you need to decide
                        how often these so called "KEEP ALIVE" messages (for obvious reasons) should
                        be sent. Sending them to often will drain the battery but on the other hand
                        sending them too slow will have the operator close the connection and force
                        the device to create a new communication (with a new IP address). The daemon
                        is clever enough to keep track of each device regardless of what IP address
                        it gets so dropping the connection is not really a big issue. The only small
                        drawback is that if its too far between the KEEP ALIVE messages it can take
                        a while to discover that the device has a problem.</para>
                    <para>The time depends on the operator but to keep the same
                            <acronym>IP</acronym> address most likely the time needs to be less than
                        2min.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Tell the tracker to start sending location updates according to
                        specifications. The tracker can be told to send back location updates at
                        regular interval (either time, distance or both). See the "track" command
                            (<xref linkend="cmd.track"/>) for more details.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
        <para>To make it easy the daemon includes a predefined <emphasis role="bold"
                >preset</emphasis> template "<filename>gtrack.preset.template</filename>". This
            preset will both enable the <acronym>GPRS</acronym> communication and also turn on
            tracking so that the device will start sending updates at specified time interval. See
                <xref linkend="section.preset-templates"/> for more details. </para>
        <para>To disable the tracking send the command "<command>set track off</command>" (see <xref
                linkend="cmd.track"/>) to the device.</para>
        <para>
            <note>
                <para>Please recall that the device by default will go into sleep mode if no
                    movement is detected within 3 minutes and will then stop sending location
                    updates.</para>
            </note>
        </para>
    </section>
</section>

