<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<section  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"  xml:id="appendix.release-history" >
    <title>Overview - Release history and roadmap</title>
    <para>For a more detailed functional description of past and future releases please see <xref
            xlink:href="#appendix.backlog"/>.  </para>
    <para>
        <note>
            <para>Version numbers indicate magnitude of change and compatibility as follows:</para>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><literal>x.y.z -> x.y.(z+1)</literal></para>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Maintenance release</emphasis> (defect or
                            optimization fixes). No change in public interface or file/DB formats.
                            Safe upgrade without user intervention..</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><literal>x.y.z -> x.(y+1).z</literal></para>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">New functionality.</emphasis> API compatibility
                            maintained. Safe upgrade but user might need to learn new functionality
                            to take advantage of release. Limited changes in DB/File format as well
                            as configuration file is possible.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><literal>x.y.z -> (x+1).y.z</literal></para>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Major new functionality.</emphasis> API
                            compatibility is not guaranteed. Any type of changes in external API,
                            file or DB format. May require a complete upgrade of config file and
                            existing DBs.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </note>
    </para>
    <section>
        <title>Major Public Releases</title>
        <para>Only rmajor new functionality is listed here.For a complete list see the NEWS file 
            (<xref xlink:href="#appendix.news" />)</para>
    <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>v3.2.0 (May 2015)</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>Introduce throttling of Google API call to avoid hitting the rate ceiling for
                        anonymous call to Google. A notification mail is now sent when the 24 hour
                        limit has been reached and further lookups are disabled until the 24 time
                        period has expired, the daemon restarted or the ".ratereset" command given.
                        Some Improvements in handling of <acronym>UTF8</acronym> characters have
                        been added and pretty-printing of tabled output introduced (see the ".table"
                        command, <xref linkend="cmd.srv-table"/>). A few more DB commands (db head,
                        db tail) and some minor bug fixes. Configuration file modified by adding
                        possibility to set a Google API key and moved the port settings to the
                        "startup" section. Improvements of the <command>dlrec</command> command and
                        some general documentation updates. Security audit for string routines and a
                        complete Coverity check. The communication with command shell was improved
                        to be able to send larger amount of data without truncation.</para>
                    <para>This release also adds the concept of "mini-maps" to the event mail as
                        well as fixes some minor bugs.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>        
            <varlistentry>
                <term>v3.1.0 (Mar 2015)</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Make it possible to connect multiple devices and select which one to
                        direct commands to. This release also makes it possible for each connected
                        command client to individually select which device to direct commands to.
                        One more highlight is the possibility to enter non-interactive commands via
                        the newly introduce "@@" command (See <xref
                            xlink:href="#sec.direct-device-commands"/>)</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>v3.0.0 (Jan 2015)</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Changed location of all data files to fully adhere to FHS (File
                        Hierarchical Standard). Added several command line options for starting the
                        daemon. Several internal changes in how the processes and locking is
                        handled. Changed configuration file content. Some minor bug fixes.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>               
            <term>v2.2.0 (Sep 2014)</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>Added reverse Geo-location address lookup to map coordinates to approximate
                        street addresses. In addition this release adds improved support for Apple
                        OS X as well as more robust USB connection handling. The build system for
                        documentation was also overhauled to improve documentation build capability
                        on most common Linux variants as well as Apple OS X. The DB schema was also
                        slightly updated to include the approx street address. In addition some
                        minor defect fixes has been included as well as a security scan of the
                        source base using coverity static code analysis.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>        
            <varlistentry>
                <term>v2.1.0 (Mar 2014)</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>This version adds full support for communication to the device over
                            <acronym>GPRS</acronym> as well as a number of internal improvements and
                        documentation updates.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>v2.0.1 (Jan 2014)</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Major DB schema improvements to increase download speed of stored location
                        on device. Added registering of devices and giving them nick-names, commands
                        for handling geo-fencing and geo-location events was added.
                            <acronym>GPX</acronym> export improved with support for identifying
                        tracks. On the server side it is now possible to list more information about
                        connected clients. The command shell was updated with improved handling of
                        long running commands (like location download). Documentation update and
                        some minor defect fixes for corner cases. </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>v1.0.1 (Jan 2014)</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>First public release</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
       
    </variablelist></section>
    <section>
        <title>High level roadmap</title>
        <para>In general the daemon is expected to initially have three to four public releases per
            year. However as it is also expected that as the product matures the updates will become
            less frequent. If critical issues with security implications are found then intermediate
            maintenance releases will issued. The daemon is considered stable with all planned
            features implemented. Future devlopment will primarily focus on making it easier to
            connect to the daemon from third party clients such as new Web clients or mobil
            clients</para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>v4.0.0 (TBD NON Committed)</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Add a Web services interface and JSON response to allow easy connection
                        from web- and mobile clients. Most likely this will technically designed
                        with a bundled HTTP server (albeit running as a separate process) to reduce
                        the need to configure an external web-server to talk to the daemon.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>        
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Upgrading to 3.2.0 from previous versions</title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">From 3.x.y</emphasis></para>
        <para>The configuration file should be refreshed from the distribution. Then it is safe to
            only replace the binaries since there is no change in data formats in any other files or
            change in file locations.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">From version 2.x.y and earlier</emphasis></para>
        <para>Due to the change in config files as well as locations of data files any older
            versions needs to be completely uninstalled before attempting to install this
            version.</para>
    </section>
</section>
