<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<appendix  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"  xml:id="appendix.trouble-shooting" >
    <title>Troubleshooting</title>
    <section>
        <title>The server is not receiving any location data</title>
        <para>Most likely caused by a router not forwarding the external port to the server or a
            firewall that is blocking the data. The method to locate such an issue is to start
            connection from the inside and then try one step out at a time until the problem can be
            repeated.</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Check that the <acronym>IP</acronym> address is correct and that the
                        daemon is able to received data.</para>
                    <para>This is most easily checked by trying to manually add a location update to
                        the daemon. First try to add a location update from the same server as the
                        one daemon is running on by using the command '<command>nc</command>' (net
                        cat) command which is a staple tool when it comes to network
                        troubleshooting.</para>
                    <para>For example if you have used the default port try</para>
                    <para>
                        <screen><emphasis role="bold">linux ></emphasis> nc localhost 3400</screen>
                    </para>
                    <para>The command above should just show an empty line indicating that the
                        connection to the server was successfull and that it is now awaiting som
                        more data, i.e. the screen should look like this</para>
                    <para>
                        <screen><emphasis role="bold">linux ></emphasis> nc localhost 3400

</screen>
                    </para>
                    <para>Precc '<command>Ctrl-C</command>' to stop the net-cat from running. We
                        have now established that the daemon is indeed listening on the correct port
                        on the server. The next step is to try to send "fake" location update string
                        manually. Since the daemon expects the incoming data to be terminated by
                            '<literal>\r\n</literal>' we use the <command>printf</command>
                        command.</para>
                    <para>
                        <screen><emphasis role="bold">linux ></emphasis> printf "3000000001,20131211002222,14.959445,58.366545,0,0,0,0,2,3.92V,0\r\n" |  
nc localhost 3400</screen>
                    </para>
                    <para>Now review the logs for the daemon to see if this location update was
                        correctly received. If this does not work then use the following
                        steps:</para>
                    <para>
                        <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>double check that the port number is correct to what you have
                                    set in the configuration file for the daemon. </para>
                                <para>When this is correct continue with next step.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>try to connect to the daemon from within your own network but
                                    from a different server than the one running the daemon. If this
                                    does not work then the problem is most likely a firewall issue
                                    on your server running the daemon. </para>
                                <para>When this works continue with next step.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>try to connect to your server from outside your own network.
                                    This will verify that your router(s) are sending through the
                                    data correctly to your server running the daemon. If this
                                    doesn't work verify your router setting so that the correct port
                                    is forwarded to the server running the daemon.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                    </para>
                    <para>If all of this works and you can send update string to your daemon
                        manually but you are still not seeing any connectsions from the device then
                        most likely the tracker device settings is missconfigured. Check your SIM
                        card provider for correct APN and a DNS server to use as well as the address
                        the tracker should connect to.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>The device is not connected via USB</title>
        <para>Most likely this is caused by wrong <acronym>USB</acronym> index. </para>
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">On Linux:</emphasis></para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Make sure that the device is not connected to your computer.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>List all <literal>ttyACM&lt;n></literal> devices with</para>
                    <para>
                        <screen><emphasis role="bold">linux ></emphasis> ls /dev/ttyACM*</screen>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Connect the device via <acronym>USB</acronym>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Again list all <literal>ttyACM&lt;n></literal> devices and compare the
                        output from above. This should show you what the <acronym>USB</acronym>
                        connection the device connects on. Now change the <acronym>USB</acronym>
                        index (in the config file or on the command line) to match the number of the
                            <literal>ttyACM&lt;n></literal></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Make sure the user running the daemon have read/write privileges on the
                        device</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">On Apple OS X:</emphasis></para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The device is one of the "<filename>/dev/cu.usbmodem????</filename>"
                        devices where the question mark is a 4 digit number that depends on where
                        you plugged the device in. Example of full paths are
                            "<filename>/dev/cu.usbmodem1411</filename>" and
                            "<filename>/dev/cu.usbmodem1451</filename>". </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The number to be specified in the config file are the last four
                        digits</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>In general if a connection cannot be established review the log file (default
                <filename>/usr/share/g7ctrl/f7ctrl.log</filename>) which might reveal further
            information.</para>
        <para>
            <note>
                <para>Please remember to wait at least 20 s after the device has been plugged in to
                    allow it to establish a connection before you try to send a command.</para>
            </note>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>An error "port is in use" is shown</title>
        <para>This means that there is a conflict between the port the daemon is trying to use and
            one of your other applications. In order to find out what application is using what port
            the easiest command that accomplish this is most likely</para>
        <para>
            <screen><emphasis role="bold">linux ></emphasis> sudo netstat -tulpn </screen>
        </para>
        <para>To find out open files use "<command>lsof</command>"</para>
    </section>
</appendix>

